As he was sitting at breakfast next morning, Basil hallwood was shown into the
room. “I am so glad I have found you, Dorian,” he said
gravely. “I called last night, and they told me you were at the opera. Of course,
I knew that was impossible. But I wish you had left word
where you had really gone to. I passed a dreadful evening, half afraid that one
tragedy might be followed by another. I think you might have telegraphed for me
when you heard of it first. I read of it
quite by chance in a late edition of The Globe that I picked up at the club. I
came here at once and was miserable at not finding you. I can’t tell you how
heartbroken I am about the whole thing. I know what you must suffer. But where were
you? Did you go down and see the girl’s mother? For a moment I thought of
following you there. They gave the address in the paper. Somewhere in the
Houston Road, isn’t it? But I was afraid of intruding upon a sorrow that I could
not not lighten. Poor woman! What a state she must be in! And her only child, too!
What did she say about it all?” “My dear Basil, how do I know?” murmured
Dorian Gray, sipping some pale yellow wine from a delicate gold beaded bubble
of Venetian glass and looking dreadfully bored. “I was at the opera. You should have
come on there. I met Lady gwendaline Harry’s sister, for the first time. We
were in her box. She is per perfectly charming; and Patty sang divinely. Don’t talk about horrid
subjects. If one doesn’t talk about a thing, it has never happened. It is simply
expression, as Harry says, that gives reality to things. I may mention that she
was not the woman’s only child. There is a son, a charming fellow, I believe. But
he's not on the stage. He is a sailor, or something. And now, tell me about yourself
and what you are painting.” “You went to the opera?” said hallwood
speaking very slowly and with a strain touch of pain in his voice. “You went to
the opera while cibil vain was lying dead in some sworded
lodging? You can talk to me of other women being charming, and of Patty
singing divinely, before the girl you loved has even the quiet of a grave to
sleep in? Why, man, there are horrors in store for that little white body of hers!”
“Stop, Basil! I won’t hear it!” cried Dorian, leaping to his feet. “You must not tell me
about things. What is done is done. What is past is past.” “You call yesterday the
past?” “What has the actual lapse of time got to do with it? It is only shallow
people who require years to get rid of an emotion. A man who is master of
himself can end a sorrow as easily as he
can invent a pleasure. I don’t want to be
at the mercy of my emotions. I want to use them, to enjoy them, and to dominate
them.” “Dorian, this is horrible! Something has changed you
completely. You look exactly the same wonderful boy who, day after day, used to
come down to my studio to sit for his picture. But you were simple, natural, and
affectionate then. You were the most unspoiled creature in the whole world.
Now, I don’t know what has come over you.
You talk as if you had no heart, no pity in you.
It is all Harry’s influence. I see that.” The lad flushed up and, going to the
window, looked out for a few moments on the green, flickering Sun lashed garden. “I
owe a great deal to Harry, Basil,” he said
at last, “more than I owe to you. You only taught me to be vain.” “Well I'm punished
for that, Dorian— —or shall be someday I don’t know what you mean, Basil,”
he exclaimed, turning round. “I don’t know what you you want. What do you
want?” “I want the Dorian Gray I used to paint,” said the artist
sadly. “Basil,” said the lad, going over to him and putting his hand on his
shoulder, “you have come too late.
Yesterday, when I heard that cibil vain had killed herself—” “Killed herself! Good
heavens! is there no doubt about that?” cried hallwood looking up at him with an
expression of horror. “My dear Basil!
Surely you don’t think it was a vulgar accident? Of course she killed herself.”
The elder man buried his face in his hands. “How fearful,” he muttered, and a
shudder ran through him. “No,” said Dorian Gray, “there is nothing
fearful about it. It is one of the great romantic tragedies of the age. As a rule,
people who act lead the most commonplace lives. They are good husbands, or faithful
wives, or something tedious. You know what I mean middleclass virtue and all that
kind of thing. How different cibil was!
She lived her finest tragedy. She was always a heroine. The last night she
played— —the night you saw her— —she acted badly because she had known the reality
of love. When she knew it's unreality, she died, as Juliet might have died. She
passed again into the sphere of art. There is something of the martyr
about her. Her death has all the pathetic uselessness of martyrdom, all it it
wasted beauty. But, as I was saying, you must not think I have not
suffered. If you had come in yesterday at a particular moment— —about halfast 5
perhaps, or a4 to 6 you would have found me in tears. Even Harry, who was here, who
brought me the news, in fact, had no idea what I was going
through. I suffered immensely. Then it passed away. I cannot repeat an emotion. No one
can, except s mentalists And you are awfully unjust, Basil. You come down here
to console me. That is charming of you.
You find me consoled, and you are furious.
How like a sympathetic person! You remind me of a story Harry told me about a
certain philanthropist who spent 20 years of his life in trying to get some
grievance redressed, or some unjust law altered— —I forget exactly what it
was. Finally he succeeded, and nothing could exceed his disappointment. He had
absolutely nothing to do, almost died of enwei and became a confirmed
misanthrop And besides, my dear old Basil, if you really want to console me, teach
me rather to forget what has happened, or to see it from a proper artistic point of
view. Was it not gotier who used to write about la desar I remember picking up a little
Vellum covered book in your studio one day and chancing on that delightful
phrase. Well, I am not like that young man you told me of when we were down at
Marlo together, the young man who used to say that yellow satin could console one
for all the miseries of life. I love beautiful things that one can touch and
handle. Old bades green bronzes lacer work carved ivories, exquisite
surroundings, luxury, pomp— —there is much to be got from all
these. But the artistic temperament that they create, or at any rate reveal, is still more to
me. To become the spectator of one’s own life, as Harry says, is to escape the
suffering of life. I know you're surprised at my talking to you like this. You have not
realized how I have developed. I was a school boy when you knew me. I am a man
now. I have new passions, new thoughts, new ideas. I am different, but you must not
like me less. I am changed, but you must always be my
friend. Of course, I am very fond of Harry.
But I know that you are better than he is. You are not stronger— —you are too much
afraid of life— —but you are better. And how happy we used to be
together! Don’t leave me, Basil, and don’t
quarrel with me. I am what I am. There is nothing more to be said.” The painter felt
strangely moved. The lad was infinitely dear to him, and and his personality had
been the great turning point in his art.
He could not bear the idea of reproaching him anymore After all, his
indifference was probably merely a mood that would pass away. There was so much in him that was
good, so much in him that was noble. “Well, Dorian,” he said at length, with
a sad smile, “I won’t speak to you again about this horrible thing, after today I
only trust your name won’t be mentioned in connection with it. The inquest is to
take place this afternoon. Have they summoned you?” Dorian shook his head, and a look of
annoyance passed over his face at the mention of the word
“inquest.” There was something so crude and vulgar about everything of the
kind. “They don’t know my name,” he answered.
“But surely she did?” “Only my Christian name, and that I am quite sure she never mentioned to
anyone She told me once that they were all rather curious to learn who I was,
and that she invariably told them my name was Prince Charming. It was pretty
of her. You must do me a drawing of syil Basil. I should like to have something
more of her than the memory of a few kisses and some broken pathetic
words.” “I will try and do something, Dorian, if it would please you. But you must come
and sit to me yourself again. I can’t get
on without you.” “I can never sit to you again, Basil. It is impossible!” he exclaimed, starting
back. The painter stared at him. “My dear boy, what nonsense!” he cried. “Do you mean
to say you don’t like what I did of you?
Where is it? Why have you pulled the screen in front of it? Let me look at it.
It is the best thing I've ever done. Do take the screen away, Dorian. It
is simply disgraceful of your servant hiding my work like that. I felt the room
looked different as I came in.” “My servant has nothing to do with it, Basil. You
don’t imagine I let him arrange my room for me? He settles my flowers for me
sometimes— —that is all. No; I did it myself.
The light was too strong on the portrait.” “Too strong! Surely not, my dear
fellow? It is an admirable place for it.
Let me see it.” And Hood walked towards the corner of the room. A cry of terror
broke from Dorian Gray’s lips, and he rushed between the painter and the screen.
“Basil,” he said, looking very pale, “you must not look at it. I don’t wish you
to.” “Not look at my own work you're not serious. Why shouldn’t I look at it?”
exclaimed hallwood laughing. “If you try to look at it, Basil,
on my word of Honor I will never speak
to you again as long as I live I'm quite serious. I don’t offer any explanation,
and you are not to ask for any. But, remember, if you touch this screen,
everything is over between us hallwood was thunder struck He looked
at Dorian Gray in absolute amazement. He had never seen him like this before. The
lad was actually palid with rage. His hands were clenched, and the pupils of
his eyes were like discs of blue fire. He was trembling all over. “Dorian!” “Don’t
speak!” “But what is the matter? Of course I
won’t look at it if you don’t want me to,”
he said, rather coldly, turning on his heel and going over towards the window.
“But, really, it seems rather absurd that I shouldn’t see my own work, especially as
I am going to exhibit it in Paris in the autumn. I shall probably have to give it
another coat of varnish before that, so I must see it someday and why not
today To exhibit it! You want to exhibit it?” exclaimed Dorian Gray, a strange sense
of terror creeping over him. Was the world going to be shown his secret? Were
people to gape at the mystery of his life? That was impossible. Something— —he did not know
what— —had to be done at once. “Yes; I don’t suppose you will object
to that George PTI is going to collect all my best pictures for a special
exhibition in the Rue Dees which will open the first week in
October. The portrait will only be away a month. I should think you could easily
spare it for that time. In fact, you are
sure to be out of town. And if you keep
it always behind a screen, you can’t care much about
it.” Dorian Gray passed his hand over his forehead. There were beads of
perspiration there. He felt that he was on the brink of a horrible danger. “You
told me a month ago that you would never exhibit it,” he cried. “Why have you changed
your mind? You people who go in for being consistent have just as many moods as
others have. The only difference is that your moods are rather meaningless. You
can’t have forgotten that you assured me most solemnly that nothing in the world
would induce you to send it to any exhibition. You told Harry exactly the same
thing.” He stopped suddenly, and a gleam of light came into his
eyes. He remembered that Lord Henry had said to him once, half seriously and half
in Gest If you want to have a strange quarter of an hour, get Basil to tell you
why he won’t exhibit your picture.
He told me why he wouldn’t, and it was a revelation to
me.” Yes, perhaps Basil, too, had his secret.
He would ask him and try. “Basil,” he said, coming over quite
close and looking him straight in the face, “we have each of us a
secret. Let me know yours, and I shall tell you mine. What was your reason for
refusing to exhibit my picture?” The painter shuddered in spite of himself.
“Dorian, if I told you, you might like me less than you do, and you would certainly
laugh at me. I could not bear your doing either of those two things. If you wish
me never to look at your picture again, I am content. I have always you to look at.
If you wish the best work I have ever done to be hidden from the world, I am
satisfied. Your friendship is dearer to me than any fame or
reputation.” “No, Basil, you must tell me,” insisted Dorian Gray. “I think I have a
right to know.” His feeling of terror had passed away, and curiosity had taken its place. He was
determined to find out Basil Hallward’s mystery. “Let us sit down, Dorian,” said the
painter, looking troubled. “Let us sit down. And just answer
me one question. Have you noticed in the picture something curious?— ?—something that
probably at first did not strike you, but that revealed itself to you suddenly?”
“Basil!” cried the lad, clutching the arms of his chair with trembling hands and
gazing at him with wild startled eyes. “I see you did. Don’t speak. Wait till
you hear what I have to say. Dorian, from the moment I met you,
your personality had the most extraordinary influence over me. I was
dominated, soul, brain, and power, by you.
You became to me the visible incarnation of that unseen ideal whose memory
haunted as artists like an exquisite dream. I worshiped you. I grew jealous of
everyone to whom you spoke. I wanted to have you all to myself. I was only happy
when I was with you. When you were away from me, you were still present in my art....
Of course, I never let you know anything about this. It would have been impossible.
You would not have understood it. I hardly understood it myself. I only knew
that I had seen perfection face to face, and that the world had become Wonder ful
to my eyes— —too wonderful, perhaps, for in such mad worships there is peril, the
peril of losing them, no less than the peril of keeping
them.... Weeks and weeks went on, and I grew more and more absorbed in you. Then came
a new development. I had drawn you as Paris in dainty armor and as Adonis with
huntsman’s cloak and polished bore spear Crowned with heavy Lotus blossoms
you had sat on the prow of adrianne's barge, gazing across the green turbid
Nile. You had leaned over the still pool of some Greek woodland and seen in the
waters silent silver the marvel of your own face. And it had all been what art should
be— —unconscious, ideal, and remote. One day, a fatal day I sometimes
think, I determined to paint a wonderful portrait of you as you actually are, not
in the costume of dead ages, but in your own dress and in your own time. Whether
it was the realism of the method, or the mere wonder of your own personality, thus
directly presented to me without mist or veil, I cannot tell. But I know that as I
worked at it, every flake and film of color seemed to me to reveal my
secret. I grew afraid that others would know of my idolatry. I felt, Dorian, that I had told
too much, that I'd put too much of myself into it. Then it was that I resolved
never to allow the picture to be exhibited. You were a little annoyed; but
then you did not realize all that it meant to me. Harry, to whom I talked about
it, laughed at me. But I did not mind that.
When the picture was finished, and I sat alone with it, I felt that I was
right.... Well, after a few days the thing left my studio, and as soon as I got rid
of the intolerable fascination of its presence, it seemed to me that I'd been
foolish in imagining that I'd seen anything in it, more than that you were
extremely good-looking and that I could paint. Even now I cannot help feeling
that it is a mistake to think that the passion one feels in creation is ever
really shown in the work one creates. Art is always more abstract than
we fancy. Form and color tell us of form and color that is
all. It often seems to me that art conceals the artist far more completely
than it ever reveals him. And so when I got this offer from Paris, I determined
to make your portrait the principal thing in my exhibition. It never occurred to me that
you would refuse. I see now that you were right. The
picture cannot be shown. You must not be angry with me, Dorian, for what I have
told you. As I said to Harry, once, you are made to be
worshiped Dorian Gray drew a long breath.
The color came back to to his cheeks, and a smile played about his lips. The peril
was over. He was safe for the time. Yet he could not help feeling infinite pity for
the painter who had just made this strange confession to him, and wondered
if he himself would ever be so dominated by the personality of a friend. Lord
Henry had the charm of being very dangerous. But that was all. He was too
clever and too cynical to be really fond of. Would there never be someone who
would fill him with a strange idolatry?
Was that one of the things that life had in store? “It is extraordinary to me,
Dorian,” said holwood that you should have seen this in the portrait. Did you really
see it?” “I saw something in it,” he answered, “something that seemed to me very
curious.” “Well, you don’t mind my looking at the thing now?” Dorian shook his head.
“You must not ask me that, Basil. I could not possibly let you stand in front of that
picture.” “You will someday surely?” “Never.” “Well, perhaps you are right. And now goodbye
Dorian. You have been the one person in my life who has really influenced my art.
Whatever I have done that is good, I owe
to you. Ah! you don’t know what it cost me
to tell you all that I've told you.” “My dear Basil,” said Dorian, “what have you
told me? Simply that you felt that you admired me too much. That is not even a
compliment.” “It was not intended as a compliment. It was a confession. Now that I've made it,
something seems to have gone out of me.
Perhaps one should never put one’s worship into words.” “It was a very disappointing
confession.” “Why, what did you expect, Dorian? You didn’t see anything else in
the picture, did you? There was nothing else to see?” “No; there was nothing else to
see. Why do you ask? But you mustn’t talk about worship. It is foolish. You and I
are friends, Basil, and we must always remain so.” “You have got Harry,” said the painter
sadly. “Oh, Harry!” cried the lad, with a ripple of laughter. “Harry spends his days
in saying what is incredible and his evenings in doing what is
improbable. Just the sort of life I would like to lead. But still I don’t think I
would go to Harry if I were in trouble. I would sooner go to you, Basil.”
“You will sit to me again?” “Impossible!” “You spoil my life as an artist by refusing,
Dorian. No man comes across two ideal things. Few come across one.” “I can’t
explain it to you, Basil, but I must never sit to you again. There is something
fatal about a portrait. It has a life of its own. I will come and have tea with
you. That will be just as pleasant.” “Pleasanter for you I'm afraid,” murmured hallwood
regretfully. “And now goodbye I'm sorry you won’t let me look
at the picture once again. But that can’t be helped. I quite understand what you
feel about it.” As he left the room, Dorian Gray smiled to himself. Poor basle How
little he knew of the true reason! And how strange it was that, instead of
having been forced to reveal his own secret, he had succeeded, almost by chance,
in resting a secret from his friend!
How much that strange confession explained to him! The painter’s absurd
fits of jealousy, his wild devotion, his extravagant panics his curious
reticences— —he understood them all now, and he felt sorry. There seemed to him to be
something tragic in a friendship so colored by romance. He sighed and touched
the bell. The portrait must be hidden away at all costs. He could not run such
a risk of discovery again. It had been mad of him to have allowed the thing to
remain, even for an hour, in a room to which any of his friends had